Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is כ״ג chaf gimmel and we pick up at
the משנה mishna in the bottom of כ״ב עמוד ב׳ chaf beis
amud beis
and we had just had this very nice passage of אגדתא aggadata
relating to a woman who might be saved because of her זכות
zechut but then the גמרא Gemara sort of on the one hand
turned it to a look at like women who appear one way
and really another way, אשה פרושה, Isha Perusha, but really then broadened
the scope to people who are men and women but very also
really focusing also a lot on men anyway who appear one way
and who are really another, again to this whole question about how
much are we focusing particularly on the woman in this the type
of a woman's type of a sin or how much are we
really sort of recognizing this as a broader phenomenon and before we
started Mike was pointing out a point I also wanted to make.
First of all I just wanted to repeat the last line of
the גמרא Gemara before the משנה mishna because it's such a good
line and in terms of distilling a certain personality type that's in
the גמרא Gemara and that's used obviously later in Rabbinic literature is
people that are מעשיהם כמעשה זמרי ומבקשים שכר כפנחס, maseihem kemaasei zimri
u'mevakshim sachar k'pinchas, that they act like a זמרי Zimri and they
expect that they're going to be rewarded like a פנחס Pinchas which
also to some degree means not only that they want to fool
other people, look how righteous they are and then in private they
go out and do things, but I think there's some even people
that in their own minds somehow have convinced themselves how righteous they
are and how they deserve all the rewards of the most righteous
people; to say הם hem the way they act is they're acting
מעשיהם כמעשה זמרי. maseihem kemaasei zimri. And I think that particularly
it's meaningful, more appropriate because here on the one hand זמרי Zimri
is somebody who just
sexually sins in public, a man again sinning and fornicating with this
Midyanite woman, and פנחס Pinchas is the קנאי, kanai, right, so it's
the קנאת אשתו kinat ishto and also קנאה kina is used in
the תורה Torah like you're מקנא mikaneh for God,
אשר קנא לאלקיו asher kina l'elohav and God is מקנא, mikaneh, right,
א-ל קנא הוא, El kana hu, and often God being מקנא mikaneh
is based on a metaphor of the jealous husband. God demands fidelity,
God demands sole worship. You worship other gods, which is also based
on a metaphor of fornication, וזנה אחרי אלהי נכר הארץ, v'zanah acharei
elohei nechar ha'aretz, and God who demands
our fidelity and our
exclusive worship we have given our worship to another god so God
is jealous. So פנחס Pinchas here is jealous for
God because this was an act that was a sin against God
and also Midyanite women so in a sense it was also an
abandonment of God because of the other gods of the other nations,
but there's a very interesting intersection of the זנות, zenut, the metaphorical
זנות zenut of abandoning God and the actual זנות zenut with the
Midyanite women. And then פנחס Pinchas is of course being
the
מקנא mikaneh so it's actually quite interesting in this context and also
making us realize this isn't just about women, it's also about men.
So with that we turn now to the next משנה, mishna, very
very long משנה mishna and let's take a look. רבי שמעון אומר
אין זכות תולה במים המרים. Rabbi Shimon omer ein zechut tola b'mayim
hamarim. No,
I deny this phenomenon that it's so funny because you could be
living a hundred years after the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and then
debating what actually happened. Okay now of course it could be that
sometimes the woman would drink the water nothing would happen so the
question is why is that? Is she genuinely innocent or is זכות
תולה? zechut tola? So it could be everybody might have agreed to
some of the observable facts; the question is what's the interpretation of
them? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I deny that ever the
merit would תולה, tola, would cause the punishment to be suspended. ואם
אתה אומר הזכות תולה, v'im atah omer hazchut tola, and my proof
that you're wrong is that it would be bad policy, that it
wouldn't be good for the reputation of the efficacy of the water.
Because if you were to say that the זכות zechut would suspend
the judgment and the effects of the water, so מדהה אתה את
המים בפני
כל הנשים. madhe ata et hamayim bifnei kol hanashim. You make it
suspect. The סיפרי Sifrei says מחשיך גונו, makhshikh gavno, you cause it
to be blurry like you cause it to lose its potency in
the eyes of everybody. People will feel it undermines the people's assumption
of its efficacy; like
literally it's like you muddy the water.
Oh that's a nice point too, you muddy the water like the
dirt that the גמרא, Gemara, that's a good point. Okay because everybody
will
say look this water doesn't work, I know this woman I actually
saw her commit adultery. And then she got away with it. מוציא
שם רע על הטהורות. Motzi shem ra al hatehorot. So number one
is you make people question the efficacy of the water, and then
you make people also question the innocent women. Suppose that, until now
we were assuming, let's say, that Rachel was innocent. Now we hear
that she might have been guilty and it might just be that
she had the זכות. zchus. שאמרו, she'omru, people will say, טמאות היו,
tmeiot hayu, they really were guilty, they committed adultery, אלא שתלתה להן
הזכות, ela shetaltah lahen hazchus,
but it's the merit that caused it to be suspended. So it
would be terrible, terrible policy, so it must be it's not true.
Right, right after they get together, right? I mean husband and wife,
no matter what, right? Unless she's dead away right away, you know?
Yeah, I mean, right. So that's also the good question that we
raised, which is if it suspends, then how does the husband know
that he can start, you know, resuming sexual relations with his wife?
Maybe, of course unless you say, no, no, no, you work with
the חזקה chazakah that it's what you observe. But it's always possible
something else, but you're entitled to work with the presumption that it
is as it's been observed. Okay, but yes, that raises a good
question. Once you often introduce that, then how can it be relied
upon, you know, even in terms of the husband and the wife?
Oh yeah, and we say resume relations so she wouldn't conceive if
she was guilty and it was put off?
Yeah, but there would be the prohibition for them to resume relations.
Right, that would be the question. Okay, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
Rebbi says, הזכות תולה במים המאררים, hazchus tola bamayim hamarerim, though it
does suspend the judgment. But and here going back actually to Davis's
point, ואינה יולדת ואינה משבחת, ve'einah yoledet ve'einah meshabbachat, and
but however, if it's only because of the זכות, zchus, obviously the
waters don't have their positive effect. It doesn't mean that she gets
her body improved, like in terms of its ability to bear children,
and she doesn't bear children. Maybe it also doesn't have the negative,
like even if she naturally would bear children, the waters still have
the effect that she's not able to bear children. And maybe what
Rebbi is saying is, and maybe that lets people know, because since
the Torah says ונקתה ונזרעה זרע, veniketah venizre'ah zara,
and then you say, hey wait, wait, she drank the water and
afterwards she didn't have kids. But the פסוק pasuk says ונקתה זרע.
veniketah zara. Ah, now we know it must have been that the
זכות zchus was תולה. tolah. And then they'll know, maybe there's a
subtle answer to your point, then they'll know that the other women
really were innocent because the other women after they went through with
it got pregnant. So maybe Rebbi sort of sees that this is
part of how people, part of the response to Rabbi Shimon. And
here it becomes even stronger. אלא מתנוונת והולכת, ela mitnavnevet veholechet,
actually not only does she not have children, but she actually deteriorates.
Okay, so people will see. Some women will drink and have children,
and their bodies will be better and they'll have a glow and
who knows what, and other women won't have children, their bodies will
deteriorate. So it'll be very clear that this person is not innocent.
וסוף היא מתה באותה מיתה, vesof hi meta be'otah mitah, and in
the end actually she will even die as a result and it'll
be the same predictable death. So it just would be a death
that would be stretched out over a longer period of time, but
it'll be very clear what the effects of the water are. Okay,
so that at least is a reasonable way of addressing Rabbi Shimon's
concerns. Again, it's interesting how we are constructing what the reality is
based on what the reality has to be. Okay, anyway, okay.
Now, moving on, that really should have been the end of the
previous משנה. Mishnah. It's funny that it was kept over till here.
נטמאת מנחתה עד שלא קדשה בכלי nitmeit minchatah ad shelo kidshah bikli
or בכלי, bekeili, הרי היא ככל המנחות ותיפדה. harei hi kechol haminchot
vetipadeh.
Let's say the מנחה minchah becomes טמא. tamei. Okay, back to the
מנחה. minchah. So presumably, we again, not exactly clear what the order
is, but let's assume that our order is based on ואחר ישקה
את המים, ve'achar yashkeh et hamayim, that you bring the מנחה, minchah,
you offer the מנחה, minchah, then she drinks the water. But now
we're doubling back, even though we just spoke about drinking the water.
So for some reason, we're doubling back to talk about the מנחה.
minchah. If the מנחה minchah became טמא tamei before it was put
in the כלי שרת, kli sharet, so then it's like all מנחות
Menachot before they've been sanctified in the vessel that can be redeemed.
Then it's just קדושת פה, kedushat peh, and a קדושת פה kedushat
peh can be transferred to money or to something else, and then
a new מנחה minchah can be brought in its stead.
ואם משיקדשה בכלי, ve'im mishekidshah bikli, but once it's been sanctified by
the כלי שרת, kli sharet, then it's considered קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf,
not just a קדושה kedushah that's been instilled in it, but an
intrinsic קדושה kedushah that defines its very identity. והרי היא ככל המנחות
ותישרף. vaharei hi kechol haminchot vetisaref. Once something has a קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, it cannot be redeemed. It cannot be taken out of
the עזרה. azarah. If it becomes טמא, tamei, it has to be
burned in the עזרה. azarah. Why are we saying all this? I
don't know, we're just telling you some of the הלכות halachot of
מנחה, minchah, and we're going to get on to the next anyway.
You're right, it's not a big חידוש chiddush in terms of general
laws of מנחות, Menachot, but it's just to establish that it is
a regular מנחה. minchah. And now we're going to get on to
something a little bit more specific.
ואלו שמנחותיהם נשרפות. ve'elu sheminchoteihem nisrafot. And the following women are those
whose מנחה minchah would be burned even though it is not טמא.
tamei. So first we want to establish here's a classic way it
would have to be burned. It became טמא tamei after it was
put in the holy vessel. That's as any מנחה. minchah. Let's now
talk about because it's a מנחת סוטה, minchat Sotah, when a unique
case is or, you know,
distinct cases that it would be burned for.
Here's some. Outside?
No, in the עזרה. azara. Once it's קדשה בכלי kadsha bekli it
cannot be taken out of the עזרה. azara.
So it's burnt in a?
Yeah, exactly. No they have some little, some little pile of ashes
where they burn things that have become פסול, psul, פסולים, psulim, קרבנות
korbanot ומהמנחות umimechanos and that's that's where it would be burnt. Okay,
so האומרת, ha'omeret, if a woman says טמאה אני לך, tmeia ani
lach,
she confesses her guilt, so she's not executed, there were not witnesses
and warning, but she confesses her guilt, there's no longer a point
of the מנחה. mincha. Okay, and therefore once it's been sanctified in
a vessel, you cannot redeem it, so you have to burn it,
but you do not go through with the process, she gets divorced
without a כתובה. kesubah. ושבאו עדים שהיא טמאה, veshebau edim shehi tmeia,
or she doesn't confess but there are witnesses, she also might not
be executed in that case if there wasn't warning, but nevertheless there's
no longer the point of going through this process, and you do
not bring the מנחה, mincha, and you would burn it, and she
would be divorced without a כתובה. kesubah. האומרת איני שותה, ha'omeret eini
shota, or she just refuses to drink. Okay, we discussed before what
if she refuses after the מגילה megillah has been scraped away, do
we allow her to refuse? But basically it's a type of a
nolo contendere, I'm not going to concede guilt, I'm not going to
admit guilt but I refuse to drink. Fine, you'll get divorced, no
כתובה kesubah because since you're the obstacle of being מברר mevarer whether
or not you're innocent or guilty, so even though we're not necessarily
saying you're guilty, but because you're right now forbidding your husband and
you're the one preventing this from moving forward, you get divorced without
a כתובה, kesubah, but we're not going to bring the מנחה, mincha,
we burn the מנחה. mincha.
What was that Latin expression?
Are you serious? Yeah. No, I think it's nolo contendere. I'm you
know, no contest. I'm not contesting the charges, I'm not pleading guilty,
I'm not pleading not guilty, I'm not contesting the charges. Right, exactly.
Is it also a form of, like have you ever pled nolo
contendere or something guilty?
Right, exactly. It's a, yeah, you can, I don't know when it's
available,
and anyway, but you can plead that.
Yeah, in the pit.
Yeah, sort of, yeah.
Okay, ושבעלה בא עליה בדרך, vesheba'ala ba aleha baderech, now there is
however a case where the husband is to blame, which is that
the husband had, well I mean you could say she's to blame,
it takes two to tango, but anyway the husband is also to
blame, they had sex on their way to the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, and he wasn't supposed to, it doesn't have to literally be
on the way, but since she became a סוטה, Sotah, and since
they're forbidden to have sex once she's a סוטה, Sotah, and it's
not ונקה האיש מעון, venika ha'ish me'avon, if he's not clean of
sin, then it will not be effective. So in that case if
we know about that and it's not effective, then you do not
bring the מנחה, mincha, we know it won't be effective. In that
case presumably she would get her כתובה kesubah because it's the husband
to blame, but we will see about that in a minute.
He doesn't actually have to go with her, does he?
I mean, wouldn't he have to? That's an interesting question, how much
because it says ויביא האיש את אשתו אל הכהן veyavi ha'ish es
ishto el hakohen etc. and he's always framed as the one who
is bringing her. I don't know, let's say he's in, I mean
you want to imagine she's not going willingly, although I guess you
could imagine she is going willingly, she's now forbidden to her husband,
she wants to prove her innocence. But like I don't know, let's
say he's infirm or whatever reason, can he just hire some of
his people to שלעפ shlep her there or whatever to represent?
You already tell me, tell me the תנחומים.
tanchumim. That's an interesting question, how much is that דווקא? davka? Yeah,
we haven't spoken about that, I don't know.
You have to show
up in court, well that's true, but you have to show up
in court if you're the,
yeah, I mean you can't, you know, you have the right to
see your accuser, but to what degree is her accuser her husband
or the witnesses that are claiming, now we do actually have witnesses
that are saying what they saw. I guess that's an interesting question
because also you could just ask it from that perspective, that if
some of these things one witness is enough, is it one witness
combined with the husband's testimony, like how much do we sort of
see the husband as a type of a testifier in this, right?
That's also an interesting question, yeah, that's a really good question, I
don't know.
Yeah, it's a border of, is this a ritual thing or a
personal thing? Right,
exactly.
Right, like you can't make a שליח shliach to be your גואל
הדם, goel hadam, you know, so I mean I think, yeah, really
is an interesting question.
ואין שליח לדבר הגוף. ve'ein shliach ledavar haguf.
Yeah, I mean if it's from
a
ritual מצוה mitzvah perspective too, correct, right. Okay, וכל הנשואות לכהנים, vechol
hanesuos lekoanim,
there you go, exactly, exactly. Can the wife send someone in her
place? It's like can you take my,
it's like can you take my urine test for
me? Right. Okay, וכל הנשואות לכהנים, vechol hanesuos lekoanim, now here's a
different הלכה halacha of נשרפות, nisrafos, but not because it's not brought,
but a different type of נשרפות, nisrafos, נשרפות nisrafos actually on the
מזבח. mizbeach. So let's take a look. וכל הנשואות לכהנים, vechol hanesuos
lekoanim, all women who are married to כהנים, kohanim, מנחתיהם נשרפות minchoseihen
nisrafos because the
הלכה halacha is מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. minchas kohen kalil
tihyeh lo te'achel. Thank you. מנחת כהן minchas kohen has to be.
be completely consumed, burnt on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So if a כהן
kohen ever brings a מנחה, mincha, a personal מנחה, mincha, it would
be burnt. Now the wife of a כהן, kohen, it's not that
she's considered a כהן, kohen, but it is considered that he is
a part owner in the מנחה. mincha. Why is he considered a
part... yes, so why is he considered a part owner in the
מנחה? mincha? So רש"י Rashi says, we're going to get to it
in the גמרא Gemara but I'll just jump ahead of it a
bit. רש"י Rashi says that a... this would be true about the
מנחה mincha that... an any מנחה mincha that a wife of a
כהן kohen would bring, it's her מנחה mincha in the sense that...
she... it's being brought for her, you know, for her... if she
made a נדר, neder, or if she has to bring it as
a... because of a type of a sin, עולה ויורד, oleh veyored,
or for this reason. She is the מתכפר, mitkapeir, she is the
one who it's representing, and on the other hand, he's the one
that foots the bill. Now תוספות Tosafos asks why does he foot
the bill? We actually have from the גמרא, Gemara, you might remember
in נזיר, Nazir, that part of the obligation of the husband is
to pay for קרבנות korbonos that the woman is obligated in. So
if it's a חטאת chatas type of an עולה ויורד oleh veyored
מנחה, mincha, or if it's a סוטה, sotah, if it's obligated, he's
paying the bill. תוספות Tosafos questions whether he's paying the bill for
a מנחת נדבה. minchas nedava. You know, he says well maybe קניין
אישה קנה בעלה, kinyan isha kana ba'alah, but if it's not really
coming out of his bank account, it's coming out of her bank
account even if technically he does have rights to it. Anyway, תוספות
Tosafos has a whole question whether this would apply to a מנחת
נדבה. minchas nedava. But it certainly applies to a מנחת סוטה minchas
sotah where he is the one that is paying because he pays
for her obligatory sacrifices but she's the one who's being brought for.
You can go even further and say also it's very distinctive about
מנחת סוטה minchas sotah because it's והביא האיש את אשתו, vehivi ha'ish
es ishto, right? And by the way, רש"י Rashi in a lot
of the earlier משניות Mishnayot says when it said that you would
bring the מנחה mincha in a כלי kli and you would transfer
to this כלי kli and you would mix it. רש"י Rashi says
the person doing the bringing the מנחה mincha is the man. Because
if you look at the פסוקים, pesukim, right, it says והביא את
קרבנה עליה. vehivi es korbonah aleha. He is מביא meivi the קרבן
korban for her. So, you know, more than any other case where
he just might be the one writing the check, you know, and
paying for it, here it's like he's bringing it for her. So
it's her מנחה mincha and it's his מנחה. mincha. So because it's
very much his מנחה mincha as well, it's the הלכה halacha that,
and he's a כהן, kohen, that it does not get, the remainder
does not get eaten, it fully gets burnt. Okay? And that's what
we're going to focus on in the גמרא Gemara is that idea.
Okay, so וכל הנסואה לכהנים מנחתיהם נשרפות. vechol hanesuah lachohanim minchateihem nisrafot.
So this burning is not burning on the floor of the עזרה
azara because it's פסול, pasul, it's burning on the altar itself.
Normally someone brings a מנחה, mincha, part of it is consumed and
part of it is,
yeah, the קומץ kometz is consumed and the remainder is eaten by
the כהנים, kohanim, the שיירים shirayim is eaten, right? And so again,
and also this נשרפות nisrafot is, a repeat, is a very different
נשרפת. nisrafet. It's a נשרפת nisrafet on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, although
we will see a little bit in the גמרא. Gemara.
Now but רש"י Rashi says, I mean you could have said that,
but רש"י Rashi anticipating that a different read of the גמרא, Gemara,
look at רש"י: Rashi: וכל הנסואה לכהנים מנחתיהם נשרפות. vechol hanesuah lachohanim
minchateihem nisrafot. רש"י Rashi says ואפילו קרב הקומץ כהלכתו ולא נטמאו נשרפים
שיירים בבית הדשן. ve'afillu karaf hakometz kiyochato velo nitme'u nisrafim shirayim beveis
hadeshen. So רש"י Rashi says no, no, no, it's the same נשרפת.
nisrafet. It's נשרפת nisrafet on the floor of the עזרה azara where
other פסול pasul things are burnt. So that's going to be interesting
because if it was really the מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen,
it would all be burnt on the altar. So we will see
two opinions in the גמרא. Gemara. Is the remainder burnt on the
altar like a real מנחת כהן, minchat kohen, or because this is
partly a מנחת כהן minchat kohen and partly the מנחה mincha of
the woman is it going to be burnt in בית הדשן?
beis hadeshen? בית הדשן beis hadeshen is outside, right, somewhere? Like isn't
that... that's like חוץ למחנה. chutz lamachaneh. No, it's...
there's a בית הדשן beis hadeshen in the עזרה. azara.
Oh, that's true. It's like a little house.
That I don't
remember, I don't remember. It's in the עזרה azara itself. Okay. Okay,
so back to the גמרא... Gemara... והכהנת שנישאת לישראל. v'hakohenet she'nisah l'Yisrael.
However, if a כהנת, kohenet, it's actually interesting, often she's called a
בת כהן, bas kohen, right? It's very interesting how much, you know,
is... does a woman sort of own her identity or identity is
via her man, especially a tribal identity, you know, besides just the
general patriarchy, it's also בית אב beis av and it's very much
identity of the tribe is through the man. So a woman, I
mean is a woman a Reuvenite or a Gadite or is she
a בת ראובן... bas Reuven... you know, is she from the tribe
of ראובן, Reuven, but her actual tribal identity is going to be
defined by the man she marries, right? So very often you have
like בת כהן, bas kohen, right? But here it's actually interesting that
it calls her a כהנת. kohenet. Okay, but that's what it means,
a woman who is... whose father is a כהן, kohen, a כהנת
kohenet in that... in that type of a woman והכהנת שנישאת לישראל
מנחתה נאכלת. v'hakohenet she'nisah l'Yisrael minchateha ne'echeles. So if she's married to
ישראל Yisrael then she doesn't have a כהן kohen status herself and
her husband isn't a כהן, kohen, so therefore it's a normal מנחה.
mincha. So therefore the קומץ kometz would be burnt on the altar
and the remainder would be eaten by the כהנים. kohanim.
מה בין כהן לכהנת? Mah bein kohen le-kohenet? What's the difference between
a כהן kohen and a כהנת? kohenet? Again, so interesting. Now we're
going to get into a משנה Mishna that enumerates a whole list
of male-female differences between כהנים kohanim and then differences between male and
female ישראלים. Yisraelim. Very interesting that we just sort of digress into
that point. Okay, and also again... Again, so interesting. Now we're going
to get into a משנה Mishna that enumerates a whole list of
male-female differences between כהנים Cohanim and then differences between male and female
ישראלים. Yisraelim. Very interesting that we just sort of digress into that
point. Okay? And also again, very interesting that it's calling her here
כהנת kohenet and not בת כהן. bat kohen. מה בין כהן לכהנת?
Ma bein kohen l'kohenet? What's the difference? מנחת כהן כהנת נאכלת. Minchat
kohen kohenet ne'echelet. The מנחה mincha of a כהנת kohenet married to
ישראל Yisrael would be eaten because she doesn't really have a כהן
kohen identity, so it's ultimately the מנחה mincha of a ישראלית. Yisraelite.
ומנחת כהן אינה נאכלת. U-minchat kohen eina ne'echelet. The מנחה mincha of
a כהן kohen is not eaten, and similarly we've seen so by
a woman married to כהן. kohen. כהנת מתחללת. Kohenet mitchalelat.
A כהנת, kohenet, her status could be, she could be a חללה.
chalalah. Her status could be violated while not just through violated of
סוטה, Sotah, but to become פסולה לכהן. psula l'kohen. If a woman
has sex with a man that is, you know, forbidden to her,
then actually, and this is interesting, it's not really a כהנת, kohenet,
it's really a, any woman, whether she's a בת כהן bat kohen
or a בת ישראלית. bat Yisraelite. If she has sex with a
man that's forbidden to her, let's say she's an אלמנה almanah that
has sex with a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, or something, let's say,
you know, she has other types of forbidden sexual acts, she becomes
considered a חללה chalalah and forbidden to a כהן. kohen. Okay? However,
so it's really not limited to כהנת. kohenet. Any woman by doing
certain forbidden sexual acts will be forbidden to a
כהן. kohen.
Even if she has sex with a non-Jew?
Yes. Although that, according to the רמב"ם, Rambam, is defined as a
זונה, zona, not a חללה, chalalah, because it's a man for whom
קידושין kiddushin would not be binding.
But things like קידושין, kiddushin, right? I mean... No, no, no.
No, no, no. Not for the status of a חללה. chalalah. No.
Status, the status of an איסור כהן issur kohen is through קידושין,
kiddushin, that's true. But status of a חללה chalalah is sex with
a man for either that the sex is forbidden or a man
that she couldn't then remarry. Okay? I mean, כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
I
thought it was a כהן גדול kohen gadol has to marry the
אלמנה almanah in that...
For him to transgress, but not for her to become a חללה.
chalalah. If he slips with a woman who's an אלמנה, almanah, then
she becomes a חללה chalalah even to a כהן הדיוט, kohen hedyot,
even though he, without the קידושין, kiddushin, actually it's a מחלוקת ראשונים.
machloket rishonim. רמב"ם Rambam says the כהן kohen only transgresses in the
context of קידושין, kiddushin, other ראשונים rishonim say without that. But her
status changes through the act of sex. Okay? So different types of
acts of sex will make a woman, whether בת כהן bat kohen
or ישראלית, Yisraelite, forbidden to a כהן. kohen. But
כהן אינו מתחלל. kohen eino mitchalel. But if the כהן, kohen, he
can do any sin under the sun, and any sexual sin, and
his כהונה kehuna status is not affected. So they can still go
up and דוכנן? duchan? Okay, so there are, there are sort of
social, you know, הלכות halachot that are based on trying to, you
know, control the situation, you know, and have sort of social censure,
and therefore a כהן kohen who is currently married to a woman
he shouldn't be married to, we don't allow to דוכנן, duchan, but
that once he divorces her we do. It's just a way of
exerting a certain type of a, you know, social control pressure on
that situation.
A כהן kohen becomes a חלל chalal only by being born from
a... exactly. כהן kohen only by being, exactly.
If a son is born a kosher כהן, kohen, he cannot... that
status cannot be lost. Okay? Which is again very like, you know,
that's really speaks
to the
disparity, thank you, lack of parallel here, you know, for in terms
of the man and the woman. But only a married woman, a
woman sleeps, a married woman sleeps with another man, it's adultery. A
married man sleeps with another woman who's not married, it's not adultery.
A woman who sleeps with another man, her status becomes, she becomes
violated, טמאה, tme'ah, forbidden to her husband. A man does, even a
man sleeps with a married woman, even a man commits adultery, he
does not become violated, right? It's again sort of the men are
the much more the actors and, you know, the women are much
more the objects as it were that can become, that their status,
you know, that they can become used and violated and, you know,
and sullied, whereas the man does not. So that's reflected here as
well by the כהונה kehuna issue.
He doesn't even get כרת? kareth?
What? Yeah, he might get חייב מיתה, chayav mita, but if he...
whatever his sin is, his status isn't affected, you know? Okay. כהנת
מטמאה למתים. Kohenet mitame'ah l'metim.
A woman who's a daughter of a כהן, kohen, you know, whatever,
a כהנת kohenet can become טמא tamei to מתים, metim, ואין כהן
מטמא למתים, ve-ein kohen mitame'ah l'metim, but a כהן kohen cannot. By
the way, the תוספתא Tosefta also has this list, and it lists
some things that are missing in the משנה Mishna like, like a
really obvious one. It says, כהנת אינה משמשת על המזבח וכהן משמש
על המזבח. Kohenet eina mshameshet al ha-mizbe'ach, ve-kohen mshamesh al ha-mizbe'ach. Like,
okay, that was a good point, right? All right. So, okay.
What do you mean
מטמאה למתים? mitame'ah l'metim?
She has no prohibition about becoming impure.
She can go to the, she
can go into a בית קברות. beit kvarot. A woman whose father
is a כהן kohen is not... she is not a כהן. kohen.
She can go into a בית קברות.
beit kvarot.
What's your problem?
Oh, I see. Okay.
כהן אוכל
בקדשי קדשים.
Kohen
ochel be-kodshei kodashim.
My question was my problem. Yeah, I know. כהן אוכל בקדשי קדשים.
Kohen ochel be-kodshei kodashim. A כהן kohen eats the holy of holies
sacrifices, the חטאת, chatat, for example, and the אשם, asham, in the
עזרה. azarah. ואין כהנת אוכלת בקדשי קדשים, Ve-ein kohenet ochelet be-kodshei kodashim,
but not a כהנת. kohenet. So basically, bottom line is, she has
no particular status as a כהנת. kohenet. I mean, that's the irony
of this משנה, Mishna, is it calls her כהנת kohenet and not
בת כהן. bat kohen. כהנת Kohenet was always, everywhere else she's called
בת כהן, bat Kohen, and bottom line is there is not one
הלכה halacha set in this משנה mishnah where she gets special status
because her father is a כהן Kohen where there's something distinct, right?
It's all the exact same as if she was a כהנת Kohenet
or
ישראלית. Yisraelit. Okay. Even מחללה michalela applies to
ישראלית. Yisraelit. Okay. כהן, Kohen, oh we did that. מה בין איש
לאשה? Mah bein ish l'ishah? Heck, while we're talking about it let's
just talk in general about differences between men and women. I mean
I guess it's relevant, we're talking about סוטה. Sotah. So okay, האיש
פורע ופורם.
Ha'ish poreia
uforem. If a man is a מצורע metzora he has to let
his hair go wild and he rends his garments, ואין האשה פורעת
ופורמת, ve'ein ha'ishah pora'at uforemet, but doesn't apply to a woman as
we will see why the גמרא Gemara learns this from. האיש מדיר
את בנו בנזיר, Ha'ish madir et beno b'nazir, and going back to
נזירות. nezirut. A man can make his son into a נזיר nazir
even if the son doesn't agree or whatever or hasn't protested, anyway,
ואין האשה מדרת את בנה בנזיר, ve'ein ha'ishah maderet et benah b'nazir,
but not a woman. האיש מגלח על נזירות אביו. Ha'ish megaleiach al
nezirut aviv. If a man's father was a נזיר nazir and the
man decided to be a נזיר nazir and the father left behind
a קרבן, korban, the man can bring it for his קרבן. korban.
I'm not going into details about that. ואין האשה מגלחת על נזירות
אביה, ve'ein ha'ishah megaleichat al nezirut avia, but that would not apply
for a woman and her father or woman and her mother, certainly
I mean doesn't even assume with the mother. האיש מקדש את בתו.
Ha'ish mekadesh et bito. A man can marry off his daughter, ואין
האשה מקדשת את בתה. ve'ein ha'ishah mekadeshet et bitah. A woman cannot.
I mean דרבנן derabbanan they created an institution where a woman could,
but דאורייתא de'oraita not. האיש מוכר את בתו. Ha'ish mocher et bito.
A man can sell off his daughter as a slave, ואין האשה
מוכרת את בתה, ve'ein ha'ishah mocheret et bitah, but not a mother
cannot sell off her daughter. האיש נסקל ערום. Ha'ish niskal arom. If
a man does a sin that he's deserving to be stoned, he's
naked when he is stoned, ואין האשה נסקלת ערומה, ve'ein ha'ishah niskelet
arumah, but not a woman. האיש נתלה. Ha'ish nitlah. If a man
after סקילה sekilah you would suspend, hang a person, so you would
do that for a man, ואין האשה נתלית, ve'ein ha'ishah nitlit, and
not a woman. האיש נמכר בגנבתו. Ha'ish nimkar bignevato. If a man
is found to be a burglar and he doesn't have the money
to pay, he would be sold into slavery, ואין האשה נמכרת בגנבתה,
ve'ein ha'ishah nimkeret bignevatah, not a woman. Of course we are missing
a few other relevant things, and if you turn for a moment
to the תוספתא, Tosefta, I don't know if you have the תוספתא,
Tosefta, תוספות Tosafot quotes it but it doesn't quote it in full,
let's just take a look if you see way in the back
of your גמרא. Gemara. Does ArtScroll have the תוספתא Tosefta in the
back?
No. מה? Mah? Sisyphus? All right, so anyway I'll read it to
you, this is פרק ב' הלכה ח' perek bet halacha chet in
the תוספתא. Tosefta. Here it is, you can if you can't find
it you can listen. כהן עומד ומקריב על גבי מזבח מה שאין
כן בכהנת. Kohen omed umakriv al gabei mizbe'ach mah she'ein kein b'Kohenet.
So that was a nice one to point out. כהן Kohen is
the one who brings the קרבנות. korbanot. האיש זכאי בבתו בקידושיה בכסף
ובשטר ובביאה. Ha'ish zakai b'bito b'kiddusheha b'kesef uvishtar uviviah.
The man has the right again to marry off the daughter, so
we sort of said that except here it also emphasizes that he
gets to keep the money, וזכאי במציאתה, v'zakai bimtziatah, he's entitled to
found objects of his daughter, ובמעשה ידיה ובהפרת נדריה, u'vma'aseh yadeha uvhafarat
nedareha, and
any labor that she does, he's entitled to annul the vows. Some
of these are might be מדרבנן, miderabbanan, but anyway most of these
are דאורייתא. de'oraita. מה שאין כן באשה, mah she'ein kein b'ishah, a
woman is not entitled, does not have those rights and privileges over
her daughter. האיש עובר על מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה. Ha'ish over al
mitzvat asei shehazman geramah. A man
will violate by not performing a positive mitzvah, or it could have
said חייב במצות עשה שהזמן גרמה, chayav b'mitzvot asei shehazman geramah, מה
שאין כן האשה, mah she'ein kein ha'ishah, a woman is not. Okay
time bound מצוות. mitzvot. האיש עובר על בל תקיף ובל תשחית. Ha'ish
over al bal takif uval tashchit. If a man shaves his sidelocks
or his beard he transgresses. ועל בל תטמא למתים, ve'al bal titama
lameitim, and not becoming tamei to the dead, assuming he's a
כהן, Kohen, מה שאין כן באשה, mah she'ein kein b'ishah, which is
not true by the woman. Let me just check. Yeah okay.
Yeah it's non-כהנים Kohanim who become טמא, tamei, מה פתאום, mah pitom,
they're just allowed.
Right, they're allowed right, and woman also becomes טמא, tamei, so it's
funny that it shifts because here really it's focusing on not specific
כהנים, Kohanim, so the טמא למתים tamei lameitim was a strange inclusion.
האיש נידון בבן סורר ומורה ואין האשה נידונית בבן סורר ומורה. Ha'ish
nidon b'ven sorer umoreh ve'ein ha'ishah nidonet b'ven sorer umoreh. Only a
boy can be a בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer umoreh, not a
girl. האיש מעטף ומספר ואין האשה מעטפת ומספרת. Ha'ish meatef umisaper ve'ein
ha'ishah meatefet umisaperet. Here it says האישה ha'ishah but it'd be ואין
האשה מעטפת ומספרת. ve'ein ha'ishah meatefet umisaperet. If a man becomes
a מצורע, metzora, it says ועל שפם יעטה, ve'al safam ya'ateh, so
this is sort of also the counterpart of letting the hair grow
wild and rending the clothes, he's supposed to sort of veil his
face, but that would not apply to a woman. האיש נמכר ונשנה.
Ha'ish nimkar venishnah. A man can be sold more than once into
slavery, ואין האשה נמכרת ונשנית, ve'ein ha'ishah nimkeret venishnet, not a woman.
I mean we said a woman can't be sold into slavery at
all, but maybe even on her own she can't resell herself into
slavery, right, because after she's freed that's the end, that's the way
the תורה Torah describes it, ויצאה חנם אין כסף. veyatza'ah chinam ein
kasef. האיש נמכר בעבד עברי ואין האשה נמכרת עבד עברי. Ha'ish nimkar
b'eved ivri ve'ein ha'ishah nimkeret eved ivri. האיש נרצע ואין האשה נרצעת
Ha'ish nirtza ve'ein ha'ishah nirtzat etc. etc. so going more to the
slave type of cases, so much more fuller list in the תוספתא.
Tosefta.
Yeah but a woman can become an indentured servant, right? אמה עברייה.
amah ivriyah.
If sold by her father.
So whether she can be sold in slavery according to this משנה
mishnah and whether she can
sell... What case? She stole,
she was found, she doesn't have the money to pay, and so
the תורה Torah says ונמכר בגניבתו, venimkar bignivato, so the גמרא's Gemara
going to say גניבתו ולא גניבתה, gnivato velo gnivatah, so the בית
דין Beis Din would not sell her, I don't know, she just
owed the money, the בית דין Beis Din would not sell
her.
And is it true that רש״י Rashi has a different גירסא girsa
of the משנה Mishnah right here? Where? האיש מוכר בתו לאמה כשהיא
קטנה. ha'ish mocher bito le'amah keshi hi ktanah.
Yeah, that's what it mentions, האיש מוכר בתו. ha'ish mocher bito. Five
lines before the end of the משנה, Mishnah, yep, first one on
the line, האיש מוכר ha'ish mocher with a little צדי tzadi by
it.
I don't know why I have האיש נמכר. ha'ish nimkar.
What? What are you looking at?
The last line of the משנה. Mishnah.
I'm not talking about the last line, five lines before the משנה
Mishnah ends, you see the little line that begins with the word
האיש ha'ish with a little צדי? tzadi?
Oh yeah, yeah, I see.
Okay, גמרא, Gemara, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. כל הנסואות לכהונה, kol hanesu'ot
likhunah, all women married to כהנים, Kohanim, מנחתם נשרפת. minchatam nisrefet. Their
מנחה mincha would be burnt. Now we have to decide what it
means to be burnt, because it's partly a מנחה mincha of a
ישראלית, Yisre'elit, which the remainder is eaten, and part status is that
of a כהן, Kohen, which its remainder should be burnt on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. So what are you going to do with it, and
where are you going to burn it? Okay, so let's take a
look. כיצד, keitzad, how is this true? כהנת לויה וישראלית, kohenet leviyah
veyisre'elit, no matter what the woman is, כהנת, kohenet, לויה leviyah or
ישראלית, yisre'elit, שנסאת לכהן, sheniset lekohen, that's married to a כהן. Kohen.
ואין מנחתה נאכלת, ve'ein minchatah ne'echelet, you can't eat the remainder of
the מנחה, mincha, מפני שיש לו חלק בה, mipnei sheyesh lo chelek
bah, because he's a part owner in it. And therefore it has
the status of מנחת כהן, minchat kohen, which it's לא תאכל, lo
te'achel, cannot be eaten. ואין עולה כליל, ve'ein olah kalil, but you
don't just burn the whole thing as one unit on the מזבח
mizbe'ach without taking a קמיצה, kmitzatah, מפני שיש לה חלק בה, mipnei
sheyesh lah chelek bah, because by a מנחה mincha of a כהן
Kohen you don't do a קמיצה, kmitzah, you just burn the whole
thing on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, but here you can't just put
the whole thing on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You have to take a
קמיצה kmitzah because it's also partly not a מנחה mincha of a
כהן. Kohen. It's a מנחה mincha of a woman, which it's not
a מנחה mincha of a כהן. Kohen. So what do you do?
You can't burn the whole thing, you can't not burn the whole
thing, what are you going to do? אלא הקומץ קרב בעצמו והשיריים
קרבים בעצמם. ela hakometz karev be'atzmo vehashirayim kreivim be'atzmam. So what you
do is you take the קמיצה kmitzah because from its identity as
a מנחת ישראל, minchat yisrael, ישראלית, yisre'elit, you have to take a
קמיצה. kmitzah. Okay, so you burn the קמיצה kmitzah separately. What do
you do? Because again as a מנחת כהן minchat kohen you just
burn the whole thing as one unit. What do you do with
the remainder? So the remainder, because of its status of מנחת כהן,
minchat kohen, you burn the remainder. So you're sort of יוצא yotzei
both. You did a קמיצה kmitzah as a מנחת ישראל minchat yisrael
and the whole thing got burnt as a מנחת כהן, minchat kohen,
which could work. The only problem is, one minute, from its status
as a מנחת ישראל, minchat yisrael, were you allowed to burn the
remainder on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Is that an acceptable thing? Good, you
did the קמיצה, kmitzah, good, you burnt it up, but were you
allowed to burn the remainder? So that's what the גמרא Gemara asks.
So the גמרא Gemara says: איכא
כאן, ika kan, one minute, you should apply here the פסוק: pasuk:
כל שהוא ממנו לאשים הרי הוא בבל תקטירו. kol shehu mimeno le'ishim
harei hu beval taktiro. Anything that part of the sacrifice was offered
up on the fire, the remainder cannot be offered. Because that's based
on the פסוק pasuk that says: כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא
תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם. ki kol se'or vechol devash lo taktiru mimeno
isheh laHashem. על המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. al hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu
lerei'ach nicho'ach. So any שאור se'or and דבש, devash, any of these
sweet things, you cannot bring from it on the מזבח mizbe'ach to
God. So the דרשה drasha is: לא תקטירו, lo taktiru, why didn't
it just say לא תקטירו על המזבח להשם? lo taktiru al hamizbe'ach
laHashem? So ממנו mimeno means anything that's from it, something has already
been offered on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the remainder cannot be offered on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Now that would apply to a שיריים shirayim of
a מנחה, mincha, but it would also apply for example to the
meat of a קרבן korban that's not an עולה. olah. You put
the innards on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the remainder that's supposed to be
eaten is forbidden to go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so the
general principle that what is not put aside by the תורה Torah
on the מזבח mizbe'ach is forbidden to be put on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So how are you allowed to do this here? Yeah. Any
קרבן korban is put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, which is then eaten,
the food that's eaten is always cooked someplace else, no? Yeah, correct.
Look, putting on the מזבח mizbe'ach doesn't mean to be eaten, means
to be offered up as a קרבן, korban, right, right, but it's
not being cooked on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, no, correct, but we learn
here that it is תקטירו, taktiru, תקטירו taktiru also means like as
a offering, but we learn here that it is forbidden to be
put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so how are you allowed to
do this? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון
בן פזי: amar Yehudah breih d'Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi: דמסיק להו לשם
עצים. demasik lehu leshem eitzim. Yeah, you treat it as wood. Like,
you're not offering it as a קרבן. korban. I'm burning the remainder
of the מנחה, mincha, it's good fuel, I'm putting it up for
fuel on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so you get to designate, that's
what it's serving as. כרבי אליעזר, keRabbi Eliezer, like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, דתניא, detanya, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says: לריח ניחוח, lerei'ach nicho'ach,
because the end of the next פסוק pasuk says: ועל המזבח לא
יעלו לריח ניחוח. ve'al hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu lerei'ach nicho'ach. So he says
לריח ניחוח lerei'ach nicho'ach frames the way you're forbidden to offer this
up. אי אתה מעלה, i atah ma'aleh, you can't offer it up
as a pleasing... pleasing fragrance to be offered as a קורבן *korbon*,
אבל אתה מעלה לשם עצים *aval ata ma'aleh l'shem eitzim*, you can
offer it as עצים *eitzim*. Now what are we talking about? This
is a similar debate, but it's a case where you got the
pieces of קורבנות *korbonos* mixed up and you don't know, you got
the big leg of lamb there, okay, but you got you got
a whole pile of legs of lambs and some of them were
from an עולה *olah* and some of them were from חטאת Chatas.
*chatas*. So the עולה *olah* ones have to be put on the
מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*, the חטאות *chata'os* are not put on the מזבח
mizbeach. *mizbeach* and are forbidden to be put. What do you do
with them? So one opinion is, well, you just got to let
them all become פסול pasul, *pasul* and burn them, like you can't
do anything, you're passive, you let it be פסול pasul *pasul* and
then you get rid of them, you burn them in a proper
way. But the other one is no, you put it all on
the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*. So the עולה *olah* legs are going on
the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*. What about the חטאת chatas *chatas* legs which
you can't identify? So they say, you know, anything here that's not
an עולה *olah*, it's just firewood, it's
fuel, it's firewood.
These are the עולות *olos* and these is the חטאות *chata'os* and
these are the others that are לשם עצים *leshem eitzim*. Exactly, exactly,
exactly.
So you do the same thing here. Now Rashi says here, Dove
mentioned the idea of a תנאי tnai, *tnai*. Rashi says here the
same idea of a תנאי tnai, *tnai*. If you look at Rashi,
Rashi says, where's Rashi? Rashi says, yes, דמסיק לשם עצים *demaseik l'shem
eitzim*, like five lines before the lines get wide, six lines before
they
get wide, Rashi says, דנימא הכי *dnema hachi*, here's what you should
say: אם ראויין הן להקטיר ולא
היתה ראויה לקמוץ *im ruyin hein l'haktir v'lo haysa ruyu l'kametz*, if
the remainder should be burnt because it really has a status of
a מנחת כהן Minchas Kohen, *minchas Kohen* and it's not, should not
even have had the קמיצה kemitza. *kmitza* taken, כדין מנחת כהן Minchas
Kohen. *k'din minchas Kohen*, הרי זו הקטרה לשמה *harei zu haktara lishmah*,
then I'm offering it as a קורבן *korbon*. דקמיצה לא מעלה ולא
מורדת *dkmitza lo ma'ala v'lo moridat*. Okay, so I separated it into
two halves, that wasn't real קמיצה kemitza, *kmitza*, then it's really just
I'm burning the whole thing, I'm offering the whole thing. ואם ראויה
היתה לקמוץ *v'im ruyu haysa l'kametz*, but if it really is like
a מנחת ישראל Minchas Yisrael. *minchas Yisrael*, ואלו שיריים *v'eilu shiyarin*, these
are the שיריים *shiyarin*, then הרי הן כשאר עצי המערכה *harei hein
k'sh'ar eitzei hamiracha*, then this is really just like firewood. Now Tosafot
says, I don't understand what that Rashi is talking about. What type
of a תנאי *tnai* is this? This is not a ספק safek,
*safek*. Like by the legs of the lamb, you don't know, is
this leg an עולה *olah* leg or a חטאת *chatas* leg? So
you know exactly what this is. This is a מנחת כהן Minchas
Kohen *minchas Kohen* and a מנחת ישראל Minchas Yisrael *minchas Yisrael* all
bundled into one. So what type of תנאי *tnai* do you make?
It's not like if it's this, if it's that. It's sort of
like, you know, it's like an אנדרוגינוס *androgynous* type of a thing,
you know, it's kind of like both statuses, like or a חצי
עבד וחצי בן חורין *chatzi eved v'chatzi ben chorin*, like you know
the מנחת חינוך chinuch, *minchas chinuch*, like he loves to ask these
questions. Okay, men are obligated, women are exempt, or men are free
people are obligated, slaves are exempt, let's say you have an אנדרוגינוס
*androgynous* or let's say you have a חצי עבד וחצי בן חורין
*chatzi eved v'chatzi ben chorin*, like how do you do it? You
know, which part, can you make your own ברכה *bracha* for yourself,
can you be מוציא *motzi* yourself, because part of you is this
and part of you is that? So you look at it two
sides of the same coin. There you go. So that's what this
is, like this is both things at once. So what type of
תנאי *tnai* do you make? So Tosafot says, you don't make a
תנאי *tnai*. Tosafot basically just says, you know, you have to just
accept the fact that essentially it seems what Tosafot is saying is,
is that what you're saying is, is that I can't, like I
am burning this but I'm, like it's not clear what Tosafot is
saying, because if you're saying like I'm treating the rest as firewood,
so then okay, so then that works from the perspective of it
being a מנחת ישראל Minchas Yisrael, *minchas Yisrael*, but for its identity
as a מנחת כהן Minchas Kohen *minchas Kohen*, you're not offering it
all up, you're offering part of it as firewood. So Tosafot never
really addresses that problem that if it's from the perspective as מנחת
כהן Minchas Kohen *minchas Kohen*, but maybe his point is, well okay,
it's not being הוקטר *huktar* as a מנחת כהן Minchas Kohen, *minchas
Kohen*, but on the other hand it's not being eaten and it's
not being burnt off of the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*. So it's the
best we can do, it's the best compromise we can do. Okay,
it's being burnt as firewood which, you know, you know what they
say, like a compromise is not when everybody is happy, a compromise
is when everybody is equally unhappy. Okay, so here everybody is equally
unhappy. It doesn't get burnt as a קורבן *korbon*, okay, so, but
it doesn't get eaten, you know, so therefore from either side it's
like a middle position. It's not getting eaten, it's not getting burnt
as a קורבן *korbon*, it's like a middle position that we take
about this. But no part of a חטאת *chatas* is ever מוקרב
*mukrov* on the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*? No, the fats are. I mean,
a חטאת פנימית *chatas pnimis* is burnt, but
that's not on המזבח *hamizbeach*.
Okay, so yeah. Isn't there a requirement for intent for in order
for it to be valid in terms of like the חטאת *chatas*
and the עולה *olah*? Yeah, I mean, you need, well first of
all סתם *stam* intent works, but you need intent for the קומץ
kometz *kometz*, but what you're asking is an excellent question which is
also the question about when you're burning the remainder לשם עצים *leshem
eitzim*, is it, does it have to satisfy the requirements of normal
הקטרה *haktara*? Like Tosafot quotes the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, can you burn the
remainder לשם עצים *leshem eitzim* at night? Can you burn the remainder
לשם עצים *leshem eitzim*, do you have to have כוונה *kavana* that
it's being as you say, that it's being brought as a קורבן
*korbon*, right? So basically if you're burning it לשם עצים *leshem eitzim*,
presumably the answer is you don't have to satisfy the requirements of
הקטרה *haktara* and you can burn it. that it's not being burnt
as a קרבן korban, and but it's not being eaten and it's
not being burnt off of the מזבח, mizbeach. it's just middle unsatisfactory,
equally unsatisfactory sort of status. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אבל אתה משיב לשנים. Aval atah meishiv lishnayim. So the
גמרא Gemara says: הניחא לרבי אליעזר. Ha nicha leRabbi Eliezer. That's good
for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאית ליה האי סברא. deise hai sevara.
He holds of this position. אלא רבנן דלית ליה האי סברא, Ella
Rabbanan deleise hai sevara, the Rabbis who disagree, they'd say that when
you have the legs of the lamb mixed up, you just, you
know, you just let them become פסול, you sit stay overnight and
then you burn them, that you're not allowed to bring it up
and declare that it's firewood. You don't get to declare it's firewood.
So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say? So
the גמרא Gemara says: Okay, דעביד ליה כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. deavid
lei keRabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon. You do like Rabbi Shimon's son, like
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon, דתניא, detanya, רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon omer: הקומץ קרב לעצמו והשיריים
מתפזרין על בית הדשן. Hakometz karev latzmo vehashiyarim mitpazrin al beis hadeshen.
And this is what רש"י Rashi referred to in the משנה. Mishnah.
Yes, this is burnt like anything else is burnt. Not I mean
the קומץ kometz is offered properly, but the remainder of it is
not burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach. The remainder of it can't be
eaten because it's partly a מנחת כהן, Minchas Kohen. and it's not
being offered on the מזבח mizbeach. because it's partly a מנחת ישראל.
Minchas Yisrael, So the קומץ kometz is offered on the מזבח mizbeiach,
but the remainder, you don't do either with it and you just
burn it on the ash pile. And that's what you do, you
can't take it out of the מזבח, mizbeiach, so you burn it
like you would sort of treat a פסול קרבן, korban, you burn
it on the ash pile. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara continues,
עמוד ב׳. amud beis. ואפילו רבנן לא פליגי עליה דרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אלא במנחת חוטא של כהנים דבת אקרבה היא. Veafillu Rabbanan lo
paligi alei deRabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon ella beMinchas Chotei shel Kohanim devas
akrava hi. Now actually, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון's Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon's
statement was not about the legs of lamb, it was about a
third scenario. The third scenario is the following: is what happens when
a כהן Kohen brings a מנחה עולה ויורד. Mincha Oleh V'Yored. Okay?
So if the כהן Kohen brings a מנחה, Mincha, there's times when
a מנחה Mincha can serve as a חטאת. It's the type of
sins that are עולה ויורד, Oleh V'Yored, that vary, you know, based
on your income, your finances. Okay? So if you're very poor you
bring a מנחה. Mincha. Now when the תורה Torah says, if a
מנחה Mincha brings, such a כהן Kohen brings such a קרבן, korban
it says the פסוק pasuk is... רש"י, Rashi, let me remind myself
what the פסוק pasuk is, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק... pasuk... the
פסוק pasuk is והייתה לכהן כמנחה. vehaysa laKohen kamincha. This shall be
for the כהן Kohen like a מנחה. Mincha. So what does that
mean? So, does that mean... so רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar
beRebbi Shimon says it means it's like a מנחת כהן. Minchas Kohen
It's like a מנחת כהן minchas kohen, means it all has to
be burnt. Okay? And the רבנן Rabbanan say no, it means it's
like a מנחת ישראל Minchas Yisrael, and therefore it... only the קומץ
kometz. is burnt. So there's a debate what does it... what happens
by... when the תורה Torah says that a מנחה Mincha of a
כהן Kohen is fully burnt, what if it's a מנחת חוטא Minchas
Chotei of a כהן? Kohen? So there's a debate whether it's burnt
or whether it's just a קומץ. komitz. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon says the whole thing is burnt. But he
also gets into this middle position because it's an interesting דרשה. drasha.
He says in its offering it's like a מנחת כהן minchas kohen
in that it all gets put like... you know, in that... like...
hold on, let me remind myself
exactly
of the דרשה.
drasha. Hold on.
שמיעת קול או ביטוי שפתים או טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. Shemias kol o
bitui sefayim o tumas mikdash vekadashav.
Okay,
so
basically here's the way it works. The רבנן Rabbanan say that it
is fully like a מנחת כהן Kohen and the whole thing gets
burnt. And רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon takes a
middle position. And רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon says
no. It doesn't say והייתה לכהן כמנחתו, vehaysa laKohen keminchaso, it doesn't
say it's for the כהן Kohen like his מנחה, Mincha, it says
כמנחה, kamincha, it's for the כהן kohen like a normal מנחה Mincha
and you do a קמיצה. On the other hand, because it also
is not a מנחת ישראל, minchas yisrael. you're not able to eat
the rest. So he gets into this similar type of a middle
position that a מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei on the one hand it's
a קמיצה, it's כמנחה kamincha like a normal מנחת ישראל, minchas yisrael.
on the other hand it's also a מנחת כהן, kohen, so you're
stuck, what do you do with the rest? He says you burn
it בבית הדשן. beveis hadeshen. And now the גמרא Gemara says that
when the Rabbis disagree and they say they burn the whole thing
on the מזבח, mizbeiach. that's only because they feel that that's not
a hybrid מנחה. Mincha. ואפילו רבנן לא פליגי עליה דרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אלא במנחת חוטא של כהנים דבת אקרבה היא. Veafillu Rabbanan lo
paligi alei deRabbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon ella beMinchas Chotei shel Kohanim devas
akrava hi. They think that's a normal מנחת כהן. kohen They think
that that would totally be burnt on the מזבח. But they would
agree that if you have a hybrid case, אבל בהא, aval behach,
this which is a hybrid case which is both מנחת כהן kohen
and מנחת ישראל, אפילו רבנן מודו, afillu Rabbanan modu, even the Rabbis
would agree that you can't eat it, you can't burn it on
the מזבח. What do you do? You burn it off of the
מזבח. Okay. Okay, so basically this is a case which רש"י Rashi
sort of speaks about as a תנאי, but it really isn't a
תנאי, a ספק, it's really a double status. And what do you
do with it? So you bring the שיירים shrayim because of its
status of מנחת ישראל. What do you do with the remainder? You
can't eat the remainder, you can't offer the remainder, so the remainder
gets burned in the floor of the עזרה. azara. The other position
is no, you burn it on the מזבח, but you treat it
like firewood. But even that position was conceding that you don't really
offer it on the מזבח, and that's your questions David, like you
wouldn't have the הלכות halachos of it could be offered at, you
know, it wouldn't have to only be a day, it wouldn't matter
what your מחשבה machshava was and so on. It would be offered
as firewood.
But then why does רש"י Rashi say
that לבית הדשן, l'beis ha-deshen, ורבי שמעון פליג ליה על הקומץ קריב
ליה לעצמו ושיירים מתפזרין לאיבוד? v'Rabbi Shimon palig lei al hakomitz kareiv
lei le'atzmo u-shrayim mitpazrin l'ibbud?
Yeah, because that's what we're saying now. We're saying that it's not
on the מזבח. Yeah, that's בית הדשן. beis ha-deshen.
That's what it means by בית הדשן, beis ha-deshen, מתפזרין לאיבוד. mitpazrin
l'ibbud.
Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא, gemara, so that was the מנחת
כהן, kohen which was the most unusual part of that משנה. mishna.
The rest of the משנה mishna just a quick list of differences
and now the גמרא's gemara just gonna give the פסוקים psukim which
are the basis for these differences. בת ישראל הנשואה לכהן, bas yisrael
hanesu'ah l'kohen, so if a בת ישראל's bas yisrael married to a
כהן kohen again as we said the קרבן has this double status
of a מנחת כהן kohen, and a מנחת ישראל. So מאי טעמא
דאמר קרא וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. mai ta'ama d'amar
kra v'chol minchas kohen kalil tihyeh lo seiachel. כהן ולא כהנת. kohen
v'lo kohenes. If it's a מנחה mincha of a כהן, kohen it's
not eaten, it's all offered up. But a מנחה mincha of a
כהנת, kohenet, meaning a בת כהן, bas kohen, is treated like a
normal מנחה mincha and you offer up the קומץ. komitz And something
that is a מנחה mincha both of the wife of a כהן
kohen. and the כהן kohen himself, it's a double status, that would
have this strange הלכה. halacha. But it starts with the idea that
a simple מנחה mincha by a non-כהן kohen even a בת כהן
bas kohen is קומץ and a מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen,
is all offered up.
Okay. כהנת מתחללת כהן אינו מתחלל. kohenet mitchaleles kohen eino mitchalel. A
woman's status can become violated or whatever, invalid for a כהן, Kohen
but the כהן status cannot, will not lose his status. So מנלן
דאמר קרא לא יחלל זרעו בעמיו. minalan d'amar kra lo yechalel zaro
b'amav. If he sleeps with a woman he's forbidden to,
he should not do that lest his child become desanctified, desacralized, or
what's another word for חלל? chalal? Defiled I guess anyway. זרעו מתחלל,
zaro mitchalel, his seed will be defiled as a result of his
forbidden sexual act. והוא אינו מתחלל v'hu eino mitchalel but his status
remains pure. Very nice. Sort of like ונקה האיש מעון. v'nikah ha-ish
mei-avon.
כהנת מתטמאה. kohenes mitameia. The woman is, the woman becomes
טמאה. tmeia. I'm sorry, a woman is allowed to become טמאה למתים
tmeia l'meisim even if she's a daughter of a כהן. מאי טעמא
דאמר קרא אמור אל הכהנים בני אהרן. mai ta'ama d'amar kra emor
el hakohanim bnei aharon. בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן. bnei aharon v'lo
bnos aharon. Right. לנפש לא יטמא בעמיו l'nefesh lo yitama b'amov is
the sons of אהרן, aharon, not the daughters of אהרן. aharon. Okay.
כהן אוכל בקדשי קדשים. kohen ochel b'kodshei kodashim. A כהן eats the
holy of holies, the חטאת and the, you know, and the מנחה
mincha etc. and the אשם. asham. דכתיב כל זכר בבני אהרן יאכלנה.
d'chsiv kol zachar bivnei aharon yochlenu. There it's very clear. All males
shall eat it. Okay. מה בין איש לאשה. ma bein ish l'isha.
Now moving from כהנים, kohanim, what's some of the differences between men
and women, again interesting the תוספתא tosefta lists I think what we
would have considered to be the most fundamental differences. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabbanan, our rabbis taught: איש אין לי אלא איש אשה מניין. ish
ein li ela ish isha minayin. How do you know that a
woman has to follow the laws of צרעת? tzara'at? If she's a
מצורע. metzora. תלמוד לומר והצרוע אשר בו הנגע. talmud lomar ve'ha-tzarua asher
bo ha-nega. Cuz it starts by saying איש איש כי יהיה בעור
בשרו בהרת לבנות. ish ish ki yihyeh b'or besaro baharet levanot. If
a man has spots. How do you know it applies to a
woman? Cuz it says והצרוע אשר בו הנגע. ve'ha-tzarua asher bo ha-nega.
And the one, and the צרוע tzarua who has the spot. Why
doesn't it, those are all extra words. It could have just gone
on to describe what his הלכה halacha is. So those extra words
are saying הרי כאן שנים. harei kan shnayim. There's another person who
can be a מצורע, metzora, not just a man, even a woman.
Equal, equal opportunities for being a מצורע. metzora. אם כן מה תלמוד
לומר איש? im kein ma talmud lomar ish? So why does it
emphasize man? לעניין שלמטה l'inyan she-lemata for some of the behaviors of
a מצורע. metzora. Not טומאה, tuma, טומאה tuma would apply equally to
a woman, but some of the other active behaviors. איש פורע ופורע.
ish poreia u-fareia. A man lets his hair grow wild and rents
his clothes etc. and not a woman.
Woman would not, oh go back to
the, going back to the becoming טמא.
tamei. What's the הוה אמינא hava amina that a woman would, I
mean, in the context
of בני
אהרן,
bnei
aharon,
וקדשו לאלהיהם, v'kiddeshu l'eloheihem, right?
Yeah but you can't say that because like the איסור issur of
becoming טמא tamei applies even when there's no בית המקדש, beis ha-mikdash,
you know?
But, I mean, the איסור טומאה issur tuma for כהנים kohanim would
apply even if they were like in חוץ לארץ, chutz l'aretz, if
they're, you know, not a, I mean but even no בית המקדש.
beis ha-mikdash. But everything the תורה torah addresses about a female in
the family of the כהנים kohanim is בת כהן. bas kohen. Right.
כי תהיה לאיש זר. ki tihiyeh l'ish zar. היא... hi...
Yeah, I mean that's the basic point the גמרא's gemara making is
that כהן is basically a male status, you know? It's about tribal
identity, it's a patriarchy or whatever and clearly a woman's status is
never the tribe she was born into, it's essentially the tribe she
marries, you know? And that's why a woman married to a כהן,
I mean, not like you have an איסור טומאה, issur tuma, but
she can eat the קרבנות korbanos etc. as תרומה truma is the
best example, right? But yeah you're right, I
mean everything... actually do also apply to women, so we don't always
say women are excluded. But anyway, but that is sort of the
default here, certainly by the כהן identity. האיש מדיר את בנו בנזיר
ואין אשה מדרת את בנה בנזיר, Ha’ish madir es bno b’Nazir v’ein
ishah maderes es bnah b’Nazir, a man can make a son a
נזיר. Nazir. Where do we know this from? אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה
היא בנזיר, Amar Rabbi Yochanan Halacha hi b’Nazir, you might remember that.
This is all הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish said some of this was about חינוך, chinuch and that חינוך
was particularly on fathers and sons and not on mothers and daughters,
but that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying here. That was
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish's take. האיש מגלח על נזירות אביו ואין אשה
מגלחת על נזירות אביה, Ha’ish megaleiach al nezirus aviv v’ein ishah megalechas
al nezirus avia, a man who became a נזיר Nazir after his
father was a נזיר Nazir can under some certain circumstances use his
father's קרבנות, Korbanos, but not a woman. אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה היא
בנזיר, Amar Rabbi Yochanan Halacha hi b’Nazir, again a הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. האיש מקדש את בתו ואין אשה מקדשת את בתה,
Ha’ish mekadesh es bito v’ein ishah mekadeshes es bita, a man can
marry off his daughter, דכתיב את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, d’ksiv es
bitti nasatti la’ish hazeh, and that was the father speaking, "I married
off my daughter." האיש מוכר את בתו ואין אשה מוכרת את בתה,
Ha’ish mocher es bito v’ein ishah mocheres es bita, a man can
sell off his daughter to slavery, דכתיב כי ימכור איש את בתו.
d’ksiv ki yimkor ish es bito. Okay. האיש נסקל ערום, Ha’ish niskal
arom, a man is stoned naked. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? ורגמו אותו
כל העדה, V’ragmu oso kol ha’eidah, they shall stone him, and אותו
oso we learn to mean we mean him alone, without his clothes.
ורגמו אותו. V’ragmu oso. So it says, so the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי אותו? mai oso? What does it mean him? אילימא אותו ולא
אותה, Ileima oso v’lo osah, that you don't stone a woman at
all, so you would never stone a woman? מאי אותו ולא אותה?
Mai oso v’lo osah? והכתיב והוצאת את האיש ההוא
או את האשה ההיא אל שעריך,
V’haksiv v’hotzeisa es
ha’ish hahu o es ha’ishah hahi el she’arecha, right? And you're going
to go ahead and execute them. אלא, Ella, so it must be
not to say that a woman doesn't get stoned or executed, but
to tell you אותו בלא כסותו ולא אותה בלא כסותה. oso b’lo
kesuso v’lo osah b’lo kesusah. אותו Oso means him alone, naked, but
you wouldn't do that with a woman. האיש נתלה, Ha’ish nisla, the
man is hanged after he's stoned. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אמר קרא
ותלית אותו על העץ, Amar Kra v’salisa oso al ha’eitz, אותו ולא
אותה. oso v’lo osah. Right, it's always a question. Since the default
gender in עברית Ivris is masculine, when do you read it to
refer only to men and not? And that
ultimately there's always going to be exceptions that we're going to say
the masculine gender doesn't actually mean that specifically. I think I mentioned
this before that I heard that now in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
they're trying to address that a little bit, at least in the
plural, and like if you have a class of like a hundred
kids and there are two boys, you'd say תלמידים, talmidim, right?
Because they're all girls you'd say תלמידות. talmidos. Apparently in עברית Ivris
there's a new pluralizing which is תלמידותים. talmidotim. So if you wanted
to say boy, men and women, not just by תלמידים, talmidim, like
a general pluralizing of
"otim." He says, "kick me."
Really? So you mean your דקדוק טוב dikduk tov is stronger than
the PC sort of gender equality though. Okay fine.
All right, anyway.
What? בנות banos and ignore the two boys that are there.
In the same way that...
but let's say it's fifty-fifty.
And those two little boys are dead.
But let's say it's
fifty-fifty. Let's say you have an audience that's fifty-fifty, should you say
כל המסובים כאן? kol hamesubim kan? Do you say כל המסובות? kol
hamesubos? I sometimes say כל המסובים והמסובות כאן. kol hamesubim v’hamesubos kan.
Maybe they'll start saying כל המסובותים כאן. kol hamesubotim kan.
ברשות כל המסובותים. Birshus kol hamesubotim. All right, I'm serious, it throws,
right? It doesn't trip up your tongue. You can see how that
become a new gender. Somebody actually said that I read somebody else
who wanted to start saying that, getting laws passed in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael where the gender is the woman, because basically there's a
principle that all laws that refer, unless specified otherwise, that
refer to a man refer
to equally refer to a woman and vice versa. So they were
trying to get like all new laws passed in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to be written in the feminine gender to presume the female
actor and not the male actor. Okay, it also applies to men,
but. All right, anyway. It's like if you ever write something and
you use the feminine pronoun, so if a person dot-dot-dot and if
she... wait, who said we're talking about a woman? Right, it's like
well I don't know who said we're talking about a man, but
again there's always clearly that bias.
Okay, education writing uses she a lot.
Yeah, a lot, I know. And once you get used to
it, somewhat weird stuff, like I try to do it sometimes in
my writing because I feel like I should, but like I'm like,
weird. Right, what's the point?
Why do you have to make a point? Why does it have
to be a woman? But
anyway, exactly. האיש נמכר בגנבתו ואין אשה נמכרת בגנבתה. Ha’ish nimkar b’gneivaso
v’ein ishah nimkeres b’gneivasah. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אמר קרא ונמכר בגנבתו.
Amar Kra v’nimkar b’gneivaso. בגנבתו ולא בגנבתה. B’gneivaso v’lo b’gneivasah. Okay.
הדרן עלך נזיר.
Hadran
alach Nazir. All right.